<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The defence of good vvomen devised and made by Sir Thomas Elyot knyght.</title>
            <author>Elyot, Thomas, Sir, 1490?-1546.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1540</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21309</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7657.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S366</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22331880</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22331880</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25385</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21309)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25385)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1751:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The defence of good vvomen devised and made by Sir Thomas Elyot knyght.</title>
                  <author>Elyot, Thomas, Sir, 1490?-1546.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[68] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In ædibus Thomæ Bertheleti typis impress.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M. D. XL [1540]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>"Cum privilegio. Ad imprimendum solum"--Colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B-D⁸ E⁶.</note>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Dated 1534 in t.p. sill.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Women --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25385:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25385:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> THE DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FENCE OF GOOD VVOMEN, DEVI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SED AND MADE BY SIR THO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAS ELYOT KNYGHT. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
            </p>
            <p>ANNO. M.D.XL.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:25385:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25385:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>TO THE MOST NOBLE AND MOSTE</hi> VER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſe princeſſe Quene Anne, wyfe vnto the moſte excellent prynce our moſte gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſe ſoueraygne lorde, kynge <hi>HENRY</hi> the. <hi>VIII.</hi> Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Elyot knyghte deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth all honour.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>FTER THAT I</hi> had diligently rad and conſidered, the lyfe and hiſtory of queene zenobia, a ladye of mooſte fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſe renoume for her excellente vertues and moſte noble courage: I was ryghte deſyrouſe, that it ſhulde be radde in our owne lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, wherby women (ſpecially) moughte be prouoked to imbrace vertue more gladly, and to be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpecte in the bryngynge vp of theyr children. But with that ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination
<pb facs="tcp:25385:3"/>there came alſo to my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce, the vngentyll cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of many men, whiche do ſet theyr delyte in rebukynge of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, althoughe they neuer recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued diſpleaſure, but often tymes benefyte by theym: ye whan theyr wanton appetite ſtereth them, they offer to ſerue them, and doo extoll them with prayſes ferre aboue rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon. which thyng I of my nature abhorrynge, determyned (for the reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that all honeſt men ought to beare to the vertuouſe and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyl ſort of good women) to prepare for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſufficient defence agaynſt yl mouthed reporters. Than forth with entred in to my fantaſy the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiſe of this lyttell treatyſe, wherin I dyd imagine, that the tyme were nowe whan zenobia lyued, whiche was about the yere after the incar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nation
<pb facs="tcp:25385:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Chryſt. CC .lxxiiii. whan alſo the noble Aureliane was Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of Rome. And to induce that noble prynceſſe to declare her owne lyfe, I deuiſed a contention betwene two gentylmen, the one named Caninins, the other Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didus. Caninius lyke a curre, at womennes condicions is alwaye barkynge, but Candidus, whiche maye be enterpreted benygne or gentyll, iudgeth euer wel, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueth but ſeldome: betwene the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> two the eſtimation of womankind commeth in queſtion. And after longe dyſputation, wherin Candi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus (as reaſon is) hathe the pree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence, at the laſte for a perfyte concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Queene Zenobia by the example of her lyfe, confirmeth his argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, and alſo vainquiſheth the obſtynate mynde of frowarde
<pb facs="tcp:25385:4"/>Caninius: and ſo endeth the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whiche I doo dedycate vnto your hyghnes mooſte noble pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, humbly deſyryng your high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in ſuche wyſe to accepte my good wyll and ſeruice and this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell warke as your owne, that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your gracis protection and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour it may ſaufely paſſe through the daungerouſe raſe of dyſdayne and enuy, and be receyued thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and ioyouſely of al good wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this your noble realme, who by the onely example of your excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent maieſtie, maye be alway deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſe to imbrace vertue and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tylneſſe, wherein conſiſteth verye nobilitie.</p>
            <q>
               <l>¶ Often readynge</l>
               <l>Cauſeth good vnderſtandynge.</l>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:25385:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>coat of arms of Sir Thomas Elyot</figDesc>
                  <head>FACE AVT TACE</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:25385:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25385:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>CANINIVS, CAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DIDVS, ZENOBIA.</head>
            <head type="sub">CANINIVS.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>VCHE IS THE</hi> condicion of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus derlynges, ſo longe as they be ſtyrred with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, they be ſtill inſenſible in the feelynge of Sapience. Ye all do knowe Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didus, kynſman to Aureliane the emperour that nowe is, an honeſt yonge gentylman, well lerned and courtayſe, ſoo that his nobleneſſe doth appere in his maners. Yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day dyd I ſee hym deuyſyng with ladies, wherby I coniected that he was a louer, and therfore I lamen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted. And as he hapned to come by me, I rouned hym in the eare and
<pb facs="tcp:25385:6"/>ſayde to hym ſoftely: Beware no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble yonge man, I perceyue ye be gyued, plucke out your legges er the boltes be ryueted. Therat he ſmyled, and layinge his hande vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon myne, he ſayde to me priuely: I wot what ye meane. I pray you be to morowe with me at Tibur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, whiche is but a lyttell out of the citie, where I haue a fayre and commodiouſe lodginge, there ſhal we ſoupe with ſome other gentyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. And there wyll I vanquiſhe your wylfull opynion conceyued agaynſt women: or elles I beinge vanquiſhed with ſufficient reaſon, wyl from henſeforth leaue al mine affection. And ſo departed he from me. This is Tiburtum, for yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is the palayce of Hadrian. well Candidus wyll not be longe, his noble nature wyl not let him breke
<pb facs="tcp:25385:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>promyſe. for lacke of faythe defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth al vertues. <hi>CANDIDVS.</hi> Ye ſpake neuer a more true ſentence, nor a more honeſt. for vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Fayth, which ſome do call truſt, is of iuſtice ſo gret a portion, that without it neyther god maye be pleaſed, nor any weale Publyke may be ſurely ſtabliſhed. And they which do lacke it them ſelfes, with a lyttell touche broken be not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle offended. <hi>CANINIVS.</hi> It is truely ſpoken, and nowe to talke of the matter, for the which ye wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led me to mete with you here is nowe happened a ryghte good oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſyon. <hi>CANDI.</hi> Ye meane the matter concernnge women, which we two now haue taken vpon vs. <hi>CANINI.</hi> Euen the ſame maſter Candidus. <hi>CANDI.</hi> Goo to on goddes name: what haue ye to
<pb facs="tcp:25385:7"/>charge with all women? <hi>CANI.</hi> Nay fyrſt I praye you tell me one thynge that I wyl aſke of you. Be not ye of that ſect of Philoſophers called <hi>Pirhonici? CANDI.</hi> What meane ye therby? I know not that ſecte: yet haue I ſene a good part of philoſophye. <hi>CANI.</hi> It is the ſect which affirmeth, that nothing is in dede as it ſeemeth to be, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge, that ſnowe is blacke and not whyte, the erthe is not ſtable but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer mouinge, &amp; many an other fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde affection, contrary to truth and al common reaſon. <hi>CANDI.</hi> No no Caninius, I neuer fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſuche vayne opinion. <hi>CANI.</hi> yet many one dothe, chaungynge onely the termes. for ſens ſnowe is ſo ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> times ſene, they feare to ſay that it is blacke, leſte they ſhulde therfore be laughed to ſcorne. But
<pb facs="tcp:25385:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>vertue, who is not ſo commonlye ſeene, and of ſoo many men loked on, is nowe of dyuerſe men ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſely eſtemed, that it is of ſome called foly, of many men fantaſy, and of ſome curioſitie. Alſo the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourers therof are lyttell ſette by, as perſones vnprofytable and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge worldely. But to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, I aſked of you, if ye were of the ſecte called <hi>Pirhonici,</hi> for if ye ſo were, I wolde thynke it vayne to reaſon thenne with you. But ye ſaye, ye be not of that ſecte, than is it as I ſayde at my fyrſt comming hyther. <hi>CANDI.</hi> What is that I praye you? <hi>CANI.</hi> ye that be lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers be dull and inſenſyble in fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge of Sapience. for althoughe ye be infourmed by dayely expery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that in woman kynde faythe neuer reſted, yet be you ſtyll as
<pb facs="tcp:25385:8"/>blind as your litel god Cupide. for the chyldiſhe affections whiche ye beare to your ladyes, cauſeth you to thynke the thynges which ye ſe, to be nothyng but vanities. <hi>CAN.</hi> Nowe in good faith that is merily ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>CA.</hi> Wel yet, ſome haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented them bitterly, fyndyng the lynke ſodainly broken, and in the ſtede of fayth falſhode &amp; trechery. <hi>CAN.</hi> Nay ye now do but rayle I promyſe you truely. In dede both by reading &amp; hereſay I haue fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d women moch blamed for theyr in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy: but for mine own know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege I neuer perceyued any ſuche lacke to be in them, but rather the contrary. <hi>CA.</hi> Syr by the conſent of al auctours my wordes be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, and your experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon therof is to be lyttell eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. <hi>CANDI.</hi> I perceiue ye be of
<pb facs="tcp:25385:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>the company, which dyſſapoynted ſomtime of your purpoſe, are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len in a freneſy, and for the diſple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of one, do ſpryng on al wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the poyſon of infamye. But nowe Caninius, ſenſe ye be wiſe and wel lerned, ſubdue your paſſion. for vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pacient hering, with wordes haſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly &amp; vnaduiſedly ſpoken, is a ſigne of foly and litel diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. wherfore now here me ſpeke thoughe it ſhal not ſauour to your opinion. The authors whom ye ſo moche do ſet by, for the more part were poetes, which ſort of perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s among the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines &amp; grekes were neuer had but in ſmal reputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For I could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer rede that in any weale publike of notable memory, Poetes were called to any honorable place, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, or dignite. Plato out of the pub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>like weale whiche he had deuyſed,
<pb facs="tcp:25385:9"/>wolde haue all poetes vtterly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded. Tulli, who next vnto Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to excelled all other in vertue and eloquence, wolde not haue in his publyke weale any poetes admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. The cauſe why they were ſoo lyttell eſtemed was, for as moche as the more parte of theyr inuenci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons conſyſted in leaſynges, or in ſterynge vp of wanton appetytes, or in pourynge oute, in raylynge, theyr poyſon of malyce. For with theyr owne goddes and goddeſſes were they ſo malaparte, that with theyr aduoutries they fylled great volumes. Iupiter, whom they cal kynge of goddes and of men, they brynge hym out of heauen to his harlottes transfourmed ſomtyme in to a bull, an other tyme lyke a ramme, a ſtynkynge gote or a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pente. His queene Iuno lyke a
<pb facs="tcp:25385:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>cowe, Mercurius lyke a wulfe. Ne they lefte heauen vnpolluted, fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge that the god Mars made Vulcane cokeolde, commyttynge aduoutrye with Venus, wyfe to Vulcanus. But Vulcane was a wyly pye and ſayde nothynge, but beinge a ſmythe, he made ſuch ſut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell manakles, that er the two lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers were ware, he tyed theym ſo faſte to gether, that they moughte not be ſeuered: and than called he the hole route of goddes and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſes, and made them to ſe Mars and Venus where they lay naked, wherat they al lewghe, but Mars was angry and Venus almoſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed. Other poetes there be, whiche in theyr moſte lamentable and wofull ditties ſo doo humble them ſelfes to theyr maiſtreſſes, as they wolde lycke the duſte frome
<pb facs="tcp:25385:10"/>theyr ſlyppers, and as ſone as ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by age, or with hauntynge of brothelles, the flame of carnalitie is throughly quenched, or elles if women do conſtantly refuſe theyr vnhoneſt deſyres, anone arme they theyr pennes and tunges with ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentyne malyce, obiecting againſt al women moſt beaſtly conditions. Wherby they more detect their pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pre inconſtancy than womens vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faythefulneſſe. <hi>CANI.</hi> Nowe in good faythe ye haue well circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed your mayſters properties. <hi>CANDI.</hi> Whom call ye my may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters? <hi>CANI.</hi> Mary poetes. for in theyr warkes is the onely ſtudy of you that be louers. for that boke, which lacketh complayntes with wepynges and ſighinges, is to you men that be amorouſe won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull tediouſe. <hi>CANDI.</hi> True<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:25385:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>Caninius ye are moche abuſed, takynge me to be of that ſorte of wantons. Nay truely, Trewe lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, of which company I confeſſe my ſelfe to be one, are in no parte of theyr conditions. for onely deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng in the honeſt behauour, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and gentylneſſe of ladies, or other matrones or damſelles, we therfore deſyre to be in theyr com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, and by mutuall deuiſinge to vſe honeſt ſolace. But ſhewe me Caninius, what other auctorytie haue ye, to proue that in womenne lacketh fidelitie. <hi>CANI.</hi> Why ſet ye ſo lyttell by poetes and poetry? <hi>CANDI.</hi> Ye whan they excede the termes of honeſtye. But if they make verſes conteynynge quicke ſentences voyd of rybauldry, or in the commendation of vertue, ſome praty allegory, or do ſet forthe any
<pb facs="tcp:25385:11"/>notable ſtory, than do I ſet by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they be well worthy. <hi>CANI.</hi> If ye wyl gyue no credence to poetes, what ſaye ye to philoſophers and writers of ſtories, with whome ye maye fynde ſuche abundaunce of examples and ſentences of the falſ hode of women and theyr vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, that if they ſhuld be reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, I trowe ye wold not abyde it, I knowe ſoo your ſhame faſtneſſe. <hi>CANDI.</hi> Truely none of theym, which were them ſelfes honeſt and continente, haue wrytten in dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prayſe of the hole kinde of women. What hath Plato, Xenophon, Plo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinus, and Plutarch, or other phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers lyke vnto them wrytten in that matter, wherby they haue made them inferiour to men? or if they haue in womenne any thinge blamed, it may appere to be but in
<pb facs="tcp:25385:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſome, and not in the more parte, if it be wel and ſyncerely conſidered. And alſo in ſtories where one wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man perchaunce is for ſome fault diſprayſed, that is counterpeyſed with a great numbre for theyr ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue commended. Now I pray you, was Helene, for whom Troy was deſtroyed (beinge rauiſhed by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris) ſo moch to be blamed, as Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinia the wyfe of Romulus, and more than a thouſand of het com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, are to be prayſed, whiche in the rage of batayle ioyned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene their huſbandes and paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, ſo reconciled theym, that with one conſent they inhabited one ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and lyued to gether in perpetu all vnitie? Ought the vnchaſtitie of any woman to be ſo remembred, as the continence of queene Pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lope oughte to be honored, who in
<pb facs="tcp:25385:12"/>the abſence of Vlixes her huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, the ſpace of .xx. yeres, kept her ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and fame vncorrupted, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandinge that with many di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe wowers ſhe was dayely aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted, but by no maner of meane moughte ſhe be founden, by dede word nor countenance in her chaſt purpoſe vnconſtant. And to reſiſt carnall affections, ſhe was alway ſene, althoughe ſhe were a queene and a kniges doughter, vertuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye occupyed. What cauſe founde Paris to forſake his firſt lady Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>none, but only that the beaulty of Helene was moche more famous? And yet his cruell vnkyndeneſſe mought not exclude loue from her gentyll harte, but ſhe remayninge ſtyll continente, after that Paris was ſlayne by Achilles, ſhe with exclamations &amp; effuſions of teres
<pb facs="tcp:25385:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>entred into the charlotte where his carcaiſe lay, and when ſhe had bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned her fayre lyppes in his putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied woundes, and had ſaciate hir ſelfe with mortall ſolace, fynallye ſhe there died oppreſſed with heui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. But bicauſe theſe be of ſome men taken for fables, I wyl brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declare the faythfulneſſe of dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe womenne reherſed in ſtories. In the hoſt of the noble kynge Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, was a great prince (as Xeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon wryteth) whoſe name was Abratades, whoo had to his wyfe a fayre lady named Panthea of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent beaulty, this prynce beinge ſlayne in batayle, ſhe attaynynge his body, and with her owne han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des waſhynge the woundes, and imbaulminge it after the facion of her owne countrey, ſhe in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Cirus, with a knife, which
<pb facs="tcp:25385:13"/>ſhe had priuely hydde, ſemynge in wordes and counteance deſirous to be with her huſband, whom ſhe mooſte tenderly loued, ſhe perced her owne harte, and with him was buried: not withſtandynge that of kynge Cirus, whom her huſband had moche prayſed a lyttel before, ſhe was in mariage deſyred. Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia, doughter to the wiſe Cato, and wyfe vnto Brutus, whan ſhe had harde of the deathe of her huſband fynding occaſion to be alone from her ſeruantes, ſhe takyng the hote burnynge coles out of a chymnay, deuoured them haſtely, and forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with died. Alſo whan Seneca by the ſentence of the cruell Nero the emperour, was condemned to die, his wife called Paulina, deſyrous to be continuall companion with her olde husbande, cauſed alſo her
<pb facs="tcp:25385:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>veines to be perced, &amp; ſo wold haue died, had not Nero commaunded her vaynes to be bounde, and the bloude to be ſtopped, ſhe notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge afterwarde lyued in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe contynuall more paynefull than deathe, and durynge her lyfe, her dedly pale colour declared to all men, whiche before knewe her, the bytter ſorowes, whiche for her huſbande ſhe alway ſuſteyned. In the tyme of the cruell confederacy of Lepidus, Octauiane, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony, a gentylman called Ligary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, was by his wife and a mayden ſeruant, kept at Rome in his houſe priuely: but what for feare of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhemente, and hope of rewarde, he at the laſt was diſcouered, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beinge ledde to be beheded, his lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge wyfe continually folowed, deſyrynge the miniſters to put her
<pb facs="tcp:25385:14"/>alſo to death with her huſband, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legyng that alſo to die ſhe had wel deſerued, for as moche as ſhe had kepte her huſbande at home, after that ſhe knew that he was attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: but ſeinge that no man dydde take regarde to her harty requeſte, ſhe returned home to her houſe, &amp; ſhuttynge faſt all the doores, and abſteynynge from all meates and drynkes, fynally with ſorowe and famyne ſhe ended her lyfe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted to her huſbande, whom ſhe ſo moche loued. But leſte we ſhuld be to longe from our ſupper, I wil ceſſe to recite any mo ſtories, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there be no lytel numbre, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge the conſtance of ladyes and damſelles. And if ye wolde ſaye, that there hath ben and is a moche greatter numbre of theym that are yll, and full of vnfaythfulneſſe, yet
<pb facs="tcp:25385:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>if that were true, than muſt ye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that in al kyndes of thinges, are commonly founde more warſe than better, or elles ſhoulde good thynges lacke theyr eſtimation, as it ſhall appere by this concluſion. for he that neuer hath ſeene any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther metall than golde, maruay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not at it, nor in his eſtimation ſetteth moch by it. And where there be none other ſtoones founde but Diamandes, Saphires, Eme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauldes, and Rubyes, there men do treade on theym, and ſell them for trifles. But if one ſhulde come to a coutreye, whiche ſemed bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayne, couered with an infynyte numbre of ſtones ragged, of yl co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and facion, if he chaunce to fynde here and there a poynted Di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>amande, well proporcioned and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rient: I dare ſaye, he wyll laye vp
<pb facs="tcp:25385:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>thoſe fewe Diamandes as a great treaſure, and not remembryng the ragged ſtones, in the beholdynge of theym take noo lyttell pleaſure. Semblably althoughe a greatte numbre of women perchance were viciouſe, yet oughte not a man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche therfore the hole kynde of women, ſenſe of them vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly many be vertuouſe. <hi>CANINI.</hi> Ye haue wel aſſembled thinges for your purpoſe. But what ſaye you to Ariſtotel, whom ye haue ſkypte ouer, in the namynge of philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers? he ſayth, that a woman is a worke of nature vnperfecte. And more ouer, that her propertie is to delyte in rebukyng, and to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way complayning, and neuer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented. Nowe take heede mayſter Candidus. Perfection is euer con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtante and neuer chaungeth, but a
<pb facs="tcp:25385:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>woman is a creatue vnperfite, ſhe therfore may neuer be ſtable or con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtante. ye knowe this fourme of argument, for I eſpy by your tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng ye ar lerned in logike. More ouer, rebukynge is a miſlykynge, and no man myſlyketh the thynge that he loueth, but all that he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth he fauoureth and lyketh, but women of theyr nature do delite in rebukynge, and the thynge wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in any perſon deliteth, he coueteth, and coueitynge it he wil at the laſt (if it be in his power) execute it. Women therfore lackinge ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, on whom they maye practiſe theyr propertie, wyll rebuke ſome time theyr husbandes, whom per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunce they loued: and than miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyketh ſhe the thing that ſhe erſt lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued. wherfore ye muſte graunte, that ſhe is vnconſtante. Alſo who
<pb facs="tcp:25385:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>that is neuer contente, maye neuer be conſtant, the cauſe why is to all men apparant. Wherfore there ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not any more argument, wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men for theſe reaſons that I haue reherſed, be of theyr nature alway vnconſtant. is it not thus? Nowe knacke me that nut mayſter Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didus. I trowe it be to harde for your teth, although ye were as wel tothed as Curins De<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tatus, which as men ſay, helde faſte a ſhyp with his tethe vntyl it was take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>CAN.</hi> In good faythe Caninius ye are a mery companyon. But althoughe my tethe be not ſo ſtrong, yet ſhal I ſoo vſe my tunge in the ſtede of my tethe, that I wyll therwith o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen your cobnut, that to all theym that wyl be contented with reaſon, it ſhall appere well, that it is pyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. <hi>CANINI.</hi> In faythe ye be a
<pb facs="tcp:25385:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>mete aduocate for women, ſenſe ye haue tethe in your tunge, for lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe haue they all, if they be toth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe. <hi>CANDI.</hi> And it ſemeth that ye lacke teth to hold in your tunge that it go not to laueſſe. But nowe wyll I aſſay to knacke your nutte maiſter Caninius. Where ye ſayd, that of a purpoſe I ſkypt ouer A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotel, there ye ſayde truely, In good faith ſo did I. And here haue at your blockehouſe, oute of the whiche is ſhot agaynſte women al this artillery. Syr whan I affyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that none of the philoſophers which were honeſt and continent, wrate any thynge in dyſprayſe of womankynde, I remembred euen than your maſter Ariſtotel, and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged hym not worthye to be of that numbre, but his reporte moch leſſe to be regarded, than the fayninges
<pb facs="tcp:25385:17"/>of poetes, whom I haue reherſed, and for this intente. For Poetes wrate agaynſte women in wanton ditties, to content men with newe fangled deuiſes. But the reproche to women, giuen by Ariſtotel, was in treatynge of matter wayghty &amp; ſeriouſe, wherby it appereth, that the ſaide wordes ſo ſpytefully ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, proceded only of cankred ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyce, whervnto he was of his own nature dyſpoſed, whiche maye be of them ſhortly perceyued, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth in his warkes, none other philoſopher eſcape vnrebuked. Ne trewelye he was aſhamed to rente with rebukes the immortall fame of Plato his mayſter, of whoſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine mouthe he had twenty yeres ſucked the moſte ſwete hony of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble philoſophye, whiche malyce grewe of this occaſion, as aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb facs="tcp:25385:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>authors haue made therof men<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion. For as moche as where he was more curyouſe in his appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayle and deckyng, than was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient to his profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, alſo more lyght in countenaunce, and diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute in lyuyng, than became an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructour of vertue and wiſedome, Plato therfore preferred other his ſcholers before hym, which he ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſpleſauntly takynge, ſoughte occaſion to rebuke his maſter wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was dead, which he neuer darſt while he was lyuynge. That Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotel was diſſolute and alſo incon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtante, it may appere by this, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is writen of him. for to Hermia whiche was his concubine he dyd ſacrifice, &amp; made ſolemne hymnes whyle ſhe was lyuynge. Canne ye compare any madneſſe or folye, to this mans abuſe and vnco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtancy?
<pb facs="tcp:25385:18"/>Maye there be ſo great an abuſe, as to gyue dyuyne honours to a mortall creature, alſo to an harlot and common ſynner? what vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy was in hym, whiche calleth that a creature vnperfyt, to whom he dyd ſolemne ſacrifice, ſange de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoute hymnes, and often tymes kneled? To blaſpheme ſo his god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe, ought not this great philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher be foule aſhamed? Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Caninius by myne aduiſe, do ye not leane more to his authorite, than vnto truthe, vertue, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie, but conſider his nature in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clyned to malyce, his fonde errour and vayne curioſite, and that whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ye diſprayſe in women, appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rante inconſtancy. <hi>CANINI.</hi> Ye haue a great affection to Plato I perceyue veryly: but wyl ye deny, that a woman is of her nature vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfecte?
<pb facs="tcp:25385:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>CANDI.</hi> ye mary wyll I. for wherin do you note her to be vnperfyte? Is it in the ſoule or in the bodye? <hi>CANI.</hi> In bothe of them trewely, for they be weaker than men, and haue theyr fleſſhe ſofter, laſſe heare on theyr viſages, and theyr voyce ſharper, and as I haue redde, they haue in ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of theyr bodyes, theyr boones fewer. And as concernynge the ſoule, they lacke hardynes, and in peryles are tunerouſe, more dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate than men, vnapte to paynful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, except they be therto conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned, or ſteryd by wylfullneſſe: And the wytte, that they haue, is not ſubſtanciall but apyſhe: neuer flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhynge but in vngraciouſeneſſe, or in trymmynge them ſelfes with praty deuyſes, or excuſynge theyr faultes with vnſtudyed anſweres,
<pb facs="tcp:25385:19"/>or in praty mockes or ſcorneful da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyaunce, or to inuent miſchieues to ſaciate theyr malice. In other thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges it is vnapt vnto knowlege, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte one or two, which I haue red of, who in Rome hath pleaded as Oratours. But that is not to be maruayled at, ſens they beinge in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in eloquence, theyr dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall exerciſe, I wyll not ſay chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge, maketh them bolde to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende in pleadynge. In the partes of wiſedome and ciuile policy, they be founden vnapte, and to haue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell capacitie. But theyr moſte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection is theyr inconſtancye, whiche procedeth of theyr ſayd na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall debilitie. For where as the affection of moche dreade or moch loue aboundeth, ſtabilitie lacketh, and wytte lyttell preuayleth. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to this I dare wel ſay, ye can
<pb facs="tcp:25385:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>make none euaſion. <hi>CAN.</hi> yes, and dyſproue all your malyciouſe concluſion. But I praye you Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimus, let me aſke you a queſtion. be all the bookes of your mayſter Ariſtotel of equal authoritie? <hi>CA.</hi> ye that be they veryly. <hi>CAN.</hi> In the inſtytution of houſeholde ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynge, called <hi>Oeconomice,</hi> Ariſtotel wryteth in this wiſe. The compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny moſte accordynge to nature, is that whiche is ordeyned of manne and woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which was conſtitute, not to the intente onely to brynge forth their ſemblable as other bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ꝑticipatours of nature &amp; with out reaſon, but for loue ſpecially, &amp; mutual aſſyſtence. And he ſayth alſo in the ſame boke, and not far from thenſe. This company is not bycauſe that eche of them hath in euery thynge and the ſame al their
<pb facs="tcp:25385:20"/>vertues lyke profytable, but ſome of theyr vertues ſeme to be contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one to an other, and yet in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion they agree to one purpoſe. for nature made man more ſtrong and couragiouſe, the woman more weake fearefull and ſcrupulouſe, to the intente that ſhe for her feble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhulde be more circumſpecte, the man for his ſtrengthe moche more aduenturouſe. Be not theſe the wordes of your maiſter? howe ſaye you? <hi>CANI.</hi> Where ye ſaye truthe I wyl not deny you. it is of his ſentence the very pythe and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. for he wrate in greke ye know well ynough. wherfore they be not in the ſame wordes as ye do ſpeke them. <hi>CAN.</hi> It maketh no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter if I do truely interprete them. But nowe to our purpoſe. Is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and vnperfection in thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,
<pb facs="tcp:25385:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>any thynge elles, than abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce and lacke of that, whiche is expedient to the ende whervnto nature hath ordeyned them? <hi>CA.</hi> Naye in good ſothe, for I thynke that a true difinition. <hi>CAN.</hi> But let me ſee, where I called it abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce,<note place="margin">Abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</note> I mought better haue na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it ſufficience.<note place="margin">Sufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</note> for abundaunce dothe properly ſignifie more than is neceſſarye. Sufficience deſcry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the thyng with boundes and limittes, the exceſſe wherof is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſuperfluitie, and the lacke may be named neceſſitie. <hi>CANI.</hi> In faythe ye be to curiouſe. Perdy the worde neyther made nor marred any thynge of our purpoſe. for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundaunce and ſufficience is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly taken for one thyng. <hi>CAN.</hi> ye and that hath ſubuerted the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of al thynge. for truely wordes
<pb facs="tcp:25385:21"/>vſed in theyr proper ſignification, do brynge thinges to a playne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandynge. And where they be moche abuſed and wreſted frome theyr trewe meanynge, they cauſe ſondry errours and perpetual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention. But let vs nowe retourne to our queſtion. Klaye is a kynde of erthe ſofte and clammy, and for thoſe qualyties ſerueth to make walles for houſes, and to that ende hath his perfection: Althoughe a ſtone be a matter harde and conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidate, and ſerueth alſo for walles, and maketh them ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger to ſerue for municion. The horſe hath mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſtrengthe, and therfore is apte for iourneys &amp; burdens: the ſhepe is feble and fearefull, &amp; maye ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore eaſely be ſhorne. And yet eche of theſe in his kynde hath his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. To men nature hath gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb facs="tcp:25385:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>puiſſaunce in membres, brau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes hard and conſolidate, the ſkyn thicke, perchance mo bones as ye ſay, to ſuſteyne outwarde labours. And to ſeme the more terrible, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che heare on theyr viſage. To wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhe hath gyuen the contrary: to thende and intente whiche your maiſter reherſed, that her debilyte ſhuld make her more circumſpect, in the kepynge (ſayth he) at home ſuche thynges as her huſbande, by his puiſſaunce hath gotten. for thoſe wordes alſo he added to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whiche are before ſpoken. Is not that a company accordynge to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, where the one dylygentelye kepeth that, whiche the other by la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bour prepareth? for what profiteth it to prepare, where ſaulfe kepinge lacketh?<note place="margin">Gettynge &amp; kepynge</note> In preparynge is labour or ſtudy, of kepynge commeth vſe
<pb facs="tcp:25385:22"/>and commodytie, and therfore to ſpeke indifferently, it deſerueth mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che more prayſe than the geatinge. But nowe tel me one thyng. wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſuppoſe you dothe a man excell all other creatures? is it in great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or puiſſance of body? <hi>CANI.</hi> No veryly. <hi>CAN.</hi> Than wherin ſuppoſe ye? <hi>CANI.</hi> In that that his ſoule is adourned with reaſon. <hi>CAN.</hi> Stop there I praye you a lyttell ſeaſon, what call ye reaſon? <hi>CANI.</hi> Why be ye nowe to lerne, what thynge is reaſon? <hi>CAN.</hi> Ye by my holy dome. And this is the cauſe. for many men leane to their ſynguler opinion, iudgyng al that is contrary, to ſtande with no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. wherfore I pray you make me therof a true definition. <hi>CANI.</hi> I wyll, to content with your fantaſy, although that ye ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do it I knowe
<pb facs="tcp:25385:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>well moche better than I.<note place="margin">Reaſon.</note> Reaſon is the principall parte of the ſoule diuine and immortal, wherby man dothe diſcerne good from yll. this thyng whyles it diſcerneth or ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the one frome the other, it is called Diſcretion:<note place="margin">Diſcretion.</note> whan it taketh the one and leaueth the other, it is named Election,<note place="margin">Election</note> iugement of ſome men. The exerciſe therof is called Prudence, of ſome Circumſpectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Prudence</note> 
               <note place="margin">Circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note>And yet is euerich of theſe thinges nothyng but reaſon, whiche to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſo propre, that lackinge it, he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his denomination. <hi>CAN.</hi> In good faith ye haue made of reaſon a ryght good deſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And now I perceyue that the thynge, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by man excelleth all other creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, is reaſon onely. <hi>CANINI.</hi> Ye veryly. <hi>CANDI.</hi> What thynke you, is reaſon onely in men? is it
<pb facs="tcp:25385:23"/>not alſo in womenne ſuppoſe you? <hi>CA.</hi> yes, that is it naturallye, for the worde Man, whiche I named, includeth as well woman as man, whan it is written or ſpoken ſo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerallye. <hi>CAN.</hi> I am glad that I haue founde you ſo reaſonable in talkynge of Reaſon. But what ſaye you by ſharpeneſſe of <hi>wytte,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Wytte.</note> doth it not betwene man and beaſt make lyke dyuerſitie? <hi>CANI.</hi> No ſuerly. for wytte is of the parte of manne that is mortall, and that is founden by dayly experyence. For where the vapours in the body be pure and ſuttell, whiche do aſcend into the brayne, the wyt becometh ſharpe and delycate: And where they be groſſe ponderouſe and ſmo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ky, the wytte is dull and nothynge pleaſant. And therfore phiſicious haue experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced by clarifying and
<pb facs="tcp:25385:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perating the corporal humours, to correcte the wytte, whiche is ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with groſſe matter oppreſſed, or with aduſt vapours ſmouldred or choked. But reaſon mought ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be brought into a beaſte, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che by nature lacketh it. And yet in dyuerſe of them haue bene percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſoo ſuttill wyttes, that therin me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue ſemed to be of them vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed. <hi>CANDI.</hi> I thynke it to be true that ye ſay. Than in whom reaſon moſte dothe appere, ye wyll affyrme, dothe moſte excell a beaſt in his nature. <hi>CANI.</hi> ye mayſter Candidus, that maye ye be ſure. <hi>CANDIDVS.</hi> And ye were agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed while ere, that to kepe diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that whiche is gotten, is worthy more prayſe than in the gettynge. <hi>CANI.</hi> ye, for there cometh more effecte of the kepynge. <hi>CANDI.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:25385:24"/>And ſo ye conclude, that the power of reaſon is more in the prudente and diligent kepynge, than in the valiaunt or politike geatyng: And that Diſcretion, Election, &amp; Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, whiche is all and in euerye parte reaſon, doo excell ſtrengthe, wytte, and hardineſſe: And conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentely they, in whome be thoſe vertues, in that that they haue them, do excell in iuſte eſtimation them that be ſtronge, hardy, or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litike in geattynge of any thynge. <hi>CA.</hi> ye haue well gathered to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all that concluſion. <hi>CANDI.</hi> Beholde Caninius, where ye be nowe: ye haue ſoo moche extolled reaſon, that in the reſpecte therof bodely ſtrength remayneth as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge: for as moch as the corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall powers with powers of the ſoule can make no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon. And
<pb facs="tcp:25385:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>ye haue not denyed, but that this worde <hi>Man,</hi> vnto whom reaſon per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyneth, doth imply in it both man and woman. And agreinge vnto Ariſtotels ſayinge, ye haue confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that prudence, whiche in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect is nothyng but reaſon, is more aptly applied to the woman, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſhe is more circumſpecte in ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynge, as ſtrengthe is to the man, that he maye be more valiaunt in geattynge. And lyke wiſe ye haue preferred the prudence in kepinge, for the vtilytie therof, before the valyauntneſſe in geattynge: And ſemblably them whiche be prudent in kepyng, before them that be on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtronge and hardy in geattinge. And ſo ye haue concluded, that wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men, which are prudent in keping, be more excellent than men in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, whiche he onelye ſtronge and
<pb facs="tcp:25385:25"/>valiaunt in geatynge. And where excellency is, there is moſte perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Wherfore a woman is not a creature vnperfyte, but as it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth is more perfyte than man. <hi>CANI.</hi> Why, haue ye dalyed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with me all this longe ſeaſon? <hi>CAN.</hi> Suerlye I haue vſed ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dalyaunce nor ſophiſtry: but if yeconſyder it wel, ye ſhal fynd it but a natural inductio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and plaine to al them that haue any capacitie. But yet haue I ſome what more to ſaye to you. Ye ſayde more ouer Caninius, that the wyttes of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were apte onely to trifils and ſhrewdenes, and not to wiſedome and ciuile policie. I wyll be plaine to you, I am ſory to fynde in your wordes ſuche maner of leudeneſſe, I crye you mercye, I wolde haue ſayde ſo moche vngentylneſſe, and
<pb facs="tcp:25385:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>in your owne wordes ſo moche for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulneſſe. <hi>CA.</hi> What meane ye therby? <hi>CANDI.</hi> ye haue twyſe graunted, that naturall reaſon is in women as well as in men. <hi>CA.</hi> ye and what then? <hi>CAN.</hi> Than haue wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo Diſcrecio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Prudence, which do make that wiſedome, whiche perteyneth to gouernaunce. And perdy, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny artes and neceſſarye occupati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons haue ben inuented by women, as I wyll brynge nowe ſome vnto your remembrance. Latine letters were fyrſt founden by Nicoſtrata, called alſo Carmentis. The .vii. li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall artes and poetry by the .ix. maydens called the Muſis. Why was Minerua honored for a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe? but bycauſe ſhe founde fyrſte in Grecia, plantynge or ſettynge of trees: alſo the vſe of armour: &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:25385:26"/>as ſome doo teſtifye, ſhe inuented makynge of fortreſſes, and many neceſſary and notable ſciences. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that the wittes of women be not vnapte to laudable ſtudies, it ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by Diotuna and Aſpaſia two honeſt maydens, whiche in al par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of philoſophy were ſo well ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that Socrates, maſter to Pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to, nothynge diſdayned to come to theyr leſſons, and called Diotima alwaye his maſtreſſe. Cleobulina, the doughter of Cleobulus, one of the ſeuen wiſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Greece, wrate diffuſe and miſtycall queſtions in heroicall verſis. Alſo Leontium a woman, excelled al menne of her tyme in wyſedome and eloquence, in ſo moche as ſhe wrate agaynſte Theophraſt, the moſt eloquent diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciple of Ariſtotel, in womennes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, whiche boke if it nowe had
<pb facs="tcp:25385:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>remayned, ſhuld haue ben ſufficy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to haue put you to ſilence. If the lernynge and wyſedome of the lady Caſſandra, doughter to king Priamus, had ben regarded more than the counſayl of flatterers, the citie of Troye and kyngedome of Frigia, hadde lenger remayned, And Priamus with his noble ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion hadde many yeres rayned. Beholde our progenitours the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Romayns in al extreme dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, whan other counſayle vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fayled, dyd not they reſort to the bokes of Sibylla Cumana, called alſo Amalthea? &amp; purſuing her ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe, which ſhe had there declared, dyd they not eſcape the perils whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thanne were imminente? Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dredes of ſuche women are in ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes remembred, but for ſpede of tyme I wyll paſſe them ouer, ſens
<pb facs="tcp:25385:27"/>I truſt that theſe be ſuffyciente to proue, that the hole kynde of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, be not vnapt vnto wiſedome as ye haue ſuppoſed. As concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge ſtrength and valyante cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, whiche ye ſurmiſe to lacke in them, I could make to you no leſſe replication, and by old ſtories and late experyence, proue, that in ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes women haue ben found of no lyttell reputation, but I wyl omit that for this tyme, for as moche as to the more parte of wyſe menne it ſhal not ſound moch to theyr com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation: Sauynge that we nowe haue one example amonge vs, as well of fortitude as of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vertues, whiche in myne opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, ſhall not be inconueniente, to haue at this tyme declared, and ſo of this matter to make a concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>CANINI.</hi> And I haue myne
<pb facs="tcp:25385:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>eares therto prepared. <hi>CAN.</hi> The beſt matter is euer good to be ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, vntyl the tale be almoſte at an ende, and than ſhal the herers with the length therof be lytel offended. Syr there dwelleth here by me a la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy, late a greate queene and wyfe to Odenatus kynge of Palmyry, whiche is a citie and countreye in Surry, her name is Zenobia: ſhe hath had of our hoſt victory twiſe, and nowe late was taken priſoner by Aurelian the emperour, all be it for her nobylitye vertue and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, ſhe was pardoned of her life, and a fayre houſe is appoynted to her in this village. ſhe is well ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in greke, and doth competent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnderſtand latine, but excellent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Egiptian language. She her ſelfe techeth her chyldren good letters, and beinge nowe vacante
<pb facs="tcp:25385:28"/>frome other buſyneſſe, wrytcth as they ſaye of Alexandria and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rient eloquent ſtories. I haue bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den her to ſupper, it wyll not nowe be longe or ſhe come hyther. And whan ye doo here her, I dare well ſaye, ye wyll be chaunged frome your opinion, and confeſſe, that in womenne is bothe courage, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and reaſon. <hi>CANINIVS.</hi> But I pray you of this matter ſay to her nothynge. <hi>CANDI.</hi> Ah, I ſee well ye be loth to come to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenynge. Thus do they all that be of your faſcion, In wyſe womens abſence ſpeke reprochefullye, and whan they be preſent, flatter them pleſauntly. But lo where ſhe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, let vs mete with her. Your ladyſhyp is very hartely welcome. <hi>ZENO.</hi> Ye haue cauſed me to do, that I haue vſed verye ſeldome.
<pb facs="tcp:25385:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>CANDI.</hi> What is that madame? <hi>ZENO.</hi> To be out of myne owne houſe at this tyme of the nyghte. <hi>CAN.</hi> I thanke therfore your la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſhyp. for I thinke the ſame, but I wyll promyſe you, nothyng ſhal come to your herynge or ſyghte, but that bothe to here and ſee may ſtand with your worſhyp. <hi>ZENO.</hi> That I hartely praye you, for the remembrance of my princely aſtate maye not ſuſteyne wordes of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſty. And bycauſe I am nowe as a priuate perſonne, I feare the common ſucceſſe of famylyaritie. <hi>CAN.</hi> What is that madame I praye you hartely. <hi>ZENO.</hi> For I drede infamy, I tell you playnely, more than euer I didde the loſſe of my lyberty. <hi>CAN.</hi> No ſuch thyng ſhall happen madame I promyſe you trewely. for here ye ſhal fynde
<pb facs="tcp:25385:29"/>nod men but of honeſte condicion. <hi>ZENOBIA.</hi> Yet ſome in deuiſing with ladies, reioyſynge to be ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hadde in a certayne ſuſpition, wyll by the way of dalyaunce con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney from them ſome thynge, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che beinge ſhewed, do ingender in the beholders ſome diſhoneſt opy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. Dyuerſe be not aſhamed, to make theyr aduant, that they haue receyued, whiche of her that they ſpeke of, was neuer ones profered. Theſe thynges maſter Candidus haue made me afrayde, to come to ſuppers and bankettes. <hi>CANI.</hi> Mary that is well ſayde. And yet ſome tyme ſuche thinges haue ben ſene offered. <hi>CANDI.</hi> Perchance of ſome yonge maydens which did it of courteſy. yet moch more haue ben aſked that haue ben denayed. I haue knowen it my ſelfe, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe
<pb facs="tcp:25385:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>you faythfully. <hi>ZENOBIA.</hi> Truely I lyke not ſuche maner of foly, I haue ben brought vp in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtudy. <hi>CANDI.</hi> I praye you madame, let me aſke you a queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but fyrſte pleaſeth it you to ſyt downe and reſte you? for I trowe your ſupper is not yet redye. <hi>ZE.</hi> Nowe what is your demaunde, ſpeke on hardily? <hi>CAN.</hi> Of what age was your ladiſhyp, whan firſt ye were maried? <hi>ZENO.</hi> Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty yeres and aboue. <hi>CANDI.</hi> It was great pitie, that ye ſoo longe taryed. <hi>ZENO.</hi> But it was the more for my commodytie. for I knewe the better what longed to my duety. <hi>CANDI.</hi> Your duety madame, what meane ye therby. <hi>ZENOBIA.</hi> For by my ſtudye in moral philoſophy, wherin I ſpent the yeres betwen ſyxtene and twen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty,
<pb facs="tcp:25385:30"/>I perceyued, that without pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtancy, wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mought be broughte lyghtely into errour &amp; foly, and made therfore vnmete for that companye, whervnto they were ordeyned: I meane, to be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence &amp; comfort to man through theyr fidelitie, whiche other beſtes are not excepte they be by the force of man therto conſtrayned. I fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d alſo, that Iuſtyce teacheth vs wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menne, to honour our huſbandes nexte after god: which honour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in due obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, wherby mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall loue betwyxte theym is in a more feruence. for vndoubtedly no woman hym loueth, whoſe hate or diſpleaſure ſhe nothynge feareth. Alſo Iuſtice reſtrayneth vs to doo any thynge,<note place="margin">Iuſtyce.</note> whiche is not ſemely. By Fortitude are we ſtyll kept in a vertuouſe conſtancy,<note place="margin">Fortitude.</note> as wel in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting
<pb facs="tcp:25385:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>affections and wanton per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion, as alſo to ſuſteyne (whan they do happen) afflyctions pacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently. But in a woman,<note place="margin">Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap> in women</note> no vertue is equall to Temperaunce, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by in her wordes and dedes ſhe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way vſeth a iuſt moderation, kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wynge whan tyme is to ſpeke, and whan to kepe ſilence, whan to be occupyed and whan to be merye. And if ſhe meaſure it to the wyll of her huſbande, ſhe dothe the more wyſely: except it may tourne them bothe to loſſe or dyſhoneſtye. yet than ſhuld ſhe ſeme rather to giue him wiſe counſaile, than to appere diſſobedient or ſturdy. In euery of theſe thynges conſiſted my duety, whiche I ſhulde not ſoo well haue knowen, if to my huſbande I had ſoner be wedded. <hi>CANI.</hi> In dede ye had ben paſte lernynge therof,
<pb facs="tcp:25385:31"/>whan ye ones had ben bedded. <hi>ZE.</hi> In good fayth ye ſaye trewely. for whan I had ben out of the dreade of my father (who kepte me in this ſtudy continuallye) and had ones taſted the pleaſaunt deuiſes, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che are prouyded for queenes and other great ladyes, ye maye well ſuppoſe I ſhulde ſone haue loſte, that delectation, whiche I had in ſtudy. <hi>CAN.</hi> Ye ſaye euen truthe by the faythe of my body. but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame, after that ye were maryed, what profite was to you, the know lege of letters? <hi>ZENO.</hi> Moche, mayſter Candidus I promyſe you veryly. for durynge the lyfe of my noble huſband of famouſe memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, I was neuer harde or ſene, ſay or do any thynge, whiche mought not contente hym, or omytte any thynge, whiche ſhulde delite hym.
<pb facs="tcp:25385:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſuch circumſpection, good lerning minyſtred vnto me, that in hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge and other paſtymes, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned alway ſuche grauitie, that of any dyſſolute appetyte, none coulde conceyue of me any ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and yet my lernynge was had of none honeſte man in any dery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon. But after the deathe of my huſbande, I founde of lernynge a meruaylouſe treaſure. For whan I conſydered the ſtate of thynges, whiche thanne hapned to gether, what daunger was to the realme immynente for lacke of a gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and that my chyldren for theyr tender youthe, ſhulde be lyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell regarded, and I beinge a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ſhoulde nothynge be feared. Alſo what tutours my chyldren ſhulde haue, it was verye vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne. Ambicion alway raigninge
<pb facs="tcp:25385:32"/>in euery countrey, whiche can not gladly ſuffer in any one perſonne ſuche maner of ſouerayntie, that vnder the name of protection, he ſhulde haue in ſubiection all the nobilitie. And althoughe that ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che one mought happen to be, yet hauynge in remembraunce as wel auncient hiſtories as late exaum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, I dradde,<note place="margin">Ambition.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Auarice.</note> leſte in ſoo greatte authoritie Ambition and Auarice mought cauſe men to forget theyr obedience truſte and fydelytie. I conſidered alſo, that the realme of Palmyry, was enuironed with en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemyes. for on the one ſyde was the hoſte of the Romaynes, which alwaye awayted to fynde oportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, to inuade my realme, and to ſubdue it vnder their Empire. The theues of Araby were on the other ſyde, whiche all redye were entred
<pb facs="tcp:25385:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>the marches, and ſpoyled the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. The kynge of Media, to be diſcharged of his trybute, ioyned with our ennemyes, wyllynge to brynge my realme in perpetuall captiuitie. Was it any meruayle, if all theſe thynges dyd excedyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly trouble me? <hi>CAN.</hi> But fynal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly madame, what remedye founde ye? <hi>ZENO.</hi> After that I hadde a lyttell bethoughte me, I determy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to prepare remedies quickely, and to ſuſteyne fortune at al times paciently. And to the intente that the name of a woman, ſhulde not amonge the people be had in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, I vſed ſo my procedynges, that none of them mought be ſayd, to be done womanly. Wherfore I ſate alway abrode amonge my no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and counſaylours, and ſayde myne opinion, ſo that it ſeemed to
<pb facs="tcp:25385:33"/>theym all, that it ſtode with good reaſon. I came often times among the people, and remembred vnto them, the libertie and honour whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che they had receyued, by the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t proweſſe of my noble huſband, ſhewynge to theym my chyldren, whiche for tender age thanne were but feble, exhortynge theym with ſondry orations to reteine theyr fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie. I viſited al the hole realme and the marches, reedified fortreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſys, and newe made alſo ſondrye municions. More ouer, I cauſed good lawes to be publyſhed, obſet uynge them fyrſte in myne owne houſeholde, and cauſed them in al other places to be well executed. I made Iuſtice chiefe ruler of myne affection, and in all conſultations wolde I be preſent, where I herde all other ſpeke fyrſte, that I wolde
<pb facs="tcp:25385:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>not be ignorant: and than ſhewed myne aduiſe, wherin I ſemed, not to be negligente. Touchynge my ſeruauntes I vſed ſuch a dilygent ſcrutiny, that they were alway per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonnes of ſynguler honeſtye. By this maner induſtry I quietly go uerned the realme of Palmyrye. And alſo added moche more to myne Empire, not ſoo moche by force, as by renoume of iuſte and politike gouernaunce, whiche all men had in ſuche admyration, that dyuerſe of our ſaid ennemies, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che agaynſte the realme erſte dyd conſpyre, and had inuaded my iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdyction, chaſe rather to leaue theyr hoſtilitie, and to remayne in our ſubiection, than to retourne to theyr owne countrey. to the whiche wyſedome and polycy I attayned by the ſtudy of noble philoſophye.
<pb facs="tcp:25385:34"/>Alſo therby I acquired ſuch mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimitie, that nowe I kepe in as ſtrayt ſubiection al affections, and paſſions, as the Romaynes doo nowe me and my chyldren. Al this conſidered, my ſtudye was to me moche more commodious bycauſe it was ſo longe or I were maryed. Wherfore I maye conclude that I had well taryed. <hi>CAN.</hi> Ye haue ſayde very well by the fayth of my body. And all that ye haue ſpoken I haue before hard as wel of your frendes as of your ennemies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed. Howe ſaye you Canmius, be you any thynge chaunged in your opinion? <hi>CANI.</hi> I wolde neuer haue loked for ſuche a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, I ſee well inoughe, that women beinge well and vertuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brought vp, do not onely with men participate in reaſon, but ſom
<pb facs="tcp:25385:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>alſo in fidelitie and conſtauncie be equall vnto them. <hi>CANDIDVS.</hi> Madame, your ſupper is redye, may it lyke you to enter in toward it. <hi>ZE.</hi> With ryght good wil: but yet if this gentylman hath aught to ſaye agaynſte women, I am not vnprouided for to defende them. <hi>CANI.</hi> Noo madame, I am by your ladyſhyp all redy ſatiſfied, he is wyſe that with reaſon is ſhorte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contented. And where Reaſon ſerueth not, ſylence is prayſed. <hi>ZENOBIA.</hi> Yet a good mynde, in ſylence, is euer well occupyed. <hi>CANDIDVS.</hi> And he that thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth well, and ſpeketh treuthe is moſte to be loued. Madame I wil leade you the waye into my houſe. <hi>ZENOBIA.</hi> With good wyll I folowe you. <hi>CANI.</hi> The conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is good, where bothe partes
<pb facs="tcp:25385:35"/>are pleaſed. And if they bothe be wyſe, it maketh no matter though fooles be offended.</p>
            <trailer>¶ Thus endeth the defence of good women.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="license">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDINI in aedibus Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae Bertheleti typis impreſſ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>CVM PRIVILEGIO. Ad imprimendum ſolum.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>ANNO. M.D.XL.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:25385:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
